A Guide to the Papers of Arthur "Bud" Metheny, 1930-1991
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Arthur "Bud" Metheny 1963-1991
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
2-8B1
9 Hollinger Document Cases, 3.75 linear feet
Metheny, Arthur
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Arthur "Bud" Metheny on January 2, 1980.
Biographical/Historical Information
Arthur Beauregard "Bud" Metheny was born July 1, 1915 in St. Louis, Missouri. He married Frances Davis of Norfolk on February 14, 1942. They had two children, Eileen and John. Metheny and his wife of 61 years, both passed away on January 2, 2003.
Metheny was a pitcher for his junior high school and American Legion teams. His father, a railroad worker, moved his family to Calverton, Virginia where Metheny attended Calverton High School. Upon graduation at 17, his mother signed a professional baseball contract for him with the New York Yankees organization. Metheny attended the College of William and Mary on a New York Yankees' scholarship where he played ball for four years. He graduated in 1940 with a B.A. in biology and physical education and in 1952, received his Masters in physical education.
After college, Metheny played minor league ball, switching from the pitchers mound to the outfield. He played for Norfolk and Kansas City, winning the pennant with both teams and Newark when the team won the Little World Series. He was called to the big leagues in 1943 and made his debut with the New York Yankees on April 27, 1943. That same year, the New York Yankees won the World Series. Metheny was the last player to wear the number 3 (Babe Ruth's number) before it was retired. In 1946, Metheny's contract was sold to the Boston Red Sox and he went back to the minors.
Metheny launched his managerial career in 1948 with the Boston Red Sox Class "D" team in Baxley, Georgia. He received a call from Joseph "Scrap" Chandler, then Norfolk Division of the College of William and Mary Athletic Director, offering Metheny the head coach position. Metheny accepted the position, which began his 32-year career at Old Dominion. Metheny continued to play minor league Class "B" ball in 1949-50 for the Portsmouth team and managed the Newport News team in 1950.
Metheny was the head baseball coach from 1948-1980 and head basketball coach from 1948-1965. He was also the Athletic Director at Old Dominion from 1963-1970. In the 1950s, Old Dominion competed in the "mythical" Little Eight Conference, which was composed of Virginia colleges. In 1962, the college joined the Mason-Dixon Conference, continuing to compete in Division II until 1976, at which time the university moved into Division I and joined the Southern Division of the Eastern College Athletic Conference.
During Metheny's tenure as head baseball coach, his teams had winning seasons in twenty-seven out of thirty-two years with a record of 423-363-6. Included among those victories were two NCAA Eastern Regional Championships, eight Little Eight Conference Championships and four Mason-Dixon Conference Championships. Metheny was honored by the NCAA as the Eastern Regional Coach of the Year in 1963 and 1964. He was also chosen as the NCAA National Coach of the Year for 1964. As head basketball coach, Metheny compiled a 198-163 record and posted sixteen winning seasons.
In 1984, Old Dominion honored Metheny by adopting a New York Yankee style uniform with blue pinstripes. Old Dominion's baseball stadium also bears his name. Metheny was inducted into the College Basketball Coaches Hall of Fame in January 1983 in Dallas, Texas. He is a member of the Virginia Sports Hall of Fame, the William and Mary Hall of Fame, the Old Dominion University Hall of Fame, and the Tidewater Baseball Hall of Fame.
June 1, 1915 Birth in St. Louis, Missouri
1932 Graduated from Calverton High School in Calverton, Virginia
1932-36 Minor League Baseball Player
1936-40 College of William and Mary
1940-43 Minor League Baseball Player
1943-46 Outfielder for the New York Yankees
1946-48 Minor League Baseball Player and Manager
1948-80 Old Dominion Head Baseball Coach
1948-65 Old Dominion Head Basketball Coach
1963-70 Old Dominion Athletic Director
1980-2003 Retirement in Virginia Beach, Virginia
January 2, 2003 Death in Virginia Beach, Virginia
Scope and Content
This collection deals primarily with Metheny's coaching career at Old Dominion.
Materials in the archives consist mainly of baseball and basketball score books, individual and team statistics, team rosters, brochures, newspaper clippings, and photographs. There is also material on the 1965 NATO Games.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically within subject groupings.
Index Terms
Metheny, Arthur; Coaches (Athletics)--United States; Old Dominion University--Basketball; Old Dominion University--Baseball; Basketball; Baseball; Sports; Brochures; Rosters; Clippings; Photographs
Contents List
- Basketball 1963-1985
  This series contains Old Dominion's basketball records from 1964-1985. The information includes score books, team rosters, brochures, NCAA standings, and assorted newspaper clippings.
  Chronological
  - Freshmen 1963-1964 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Varsity 1965-1966 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Freshmen 1965-1966 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Varsity 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Freshmen 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Varsity 1967-1968 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Freshmen 1967-1968 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Varsity 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Freshmen 1968-1969 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Varsity 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Freshmen 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Varsity 1970-1971 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Freshmen 1970-1971 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Varsity 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Freshmen 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Varsity 1972-1973 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Varsity 1973-1974 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Junior Varsity 1973-1974 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Varsity 1975-1976 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Exhibition Score Book 1975 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Score Book 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Varsity 1977-1978 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Varsity 1978-1979 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Varsity 1979-1980 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Score Book 1980-1981 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Score Book 1981-1982 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Basketball 1982-1983 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Basketball 1983-1984 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Basketball 1984-1985 (Box-folder 4:4)
- Baseball 1951-1991
  This series contains Old Dominion's baseball records from 1951 through 1991. The material includes team and individual statistics, score books, and student papers on the history of Old Dominion baseball.
  - HPE 339 Baseball Statistics (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Baseball 1951,1953 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Scorebook 1952-1956 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Scorebook 1957-1960 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Scorebook 1961-1965 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Baseball 1962 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Varsity 1963 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Varsity 1964 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Cumulative Stats 1965 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Score Book 1966-1967 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Score Book 1966-1969,1971 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Cumulative Stats 1966 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Cumulative Stats 1967 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Cumulative Stats 1968 (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Cumulative Stats 1969-1971 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Cumulative Stats (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Score Book 1972-1976 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Cumulative Stats 1972 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Cumulative Stats 1973 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Cumulative Stats 1974 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Cumulative Stats 1975 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Cumulative Stats 1976 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Score Book 1977-1980 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Cumulative Stats 1978 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Score Book 1979 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Baseball Brochure 1980 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Score Book 1984-1985 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Score Book 1985-1986 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Score Book 1987 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Score Book 1988 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Score Book 1989 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Baseball Photographs and News Clippings (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Score Book 1990 (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Score Book 1991 (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Baseball Statistics Miscellaneous (Box-folder 8:6)
- Sporting Events 1964-1965
  This series contains Arthur Metheny's records on the 1964 Tidewater Games and the 1965 NATO Games. The information contains correspondence, rosters, and newspaper clippings. Material is arranged
  - Tidewater Relays 1964 (Box-folder 8:7)
  - NATO Games 1965 (Box-folder 8:8)
  - NATO Games Newspaper Clippings 1965 (Box-folder 8:9)
- Photographs 1930-1989
  This series consists of two bound books of basketball team photographs.
  - Basketball Team Photos 1930-1960 (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Basketball Team Photos 1960-1989 (Box-folder 9:2)